hello everyone and welcome to the shadow
proof YouTube Welcome
um here for another conversation but
before we get going I just want to take
a moment to encourage you to subscribe
to the channel you'll get alerts when we
post new content you'll know when we're
having conversations like this one and
then also become a subscriber go to the
center.org get a regular updates on
whistleblower stories as well as the
latest developments on WikiLeaks founder
Julian assange's case uh without with
that out of the way let's get to today's
conversation I'm joined by my friend and
colleague John kiriaku who is a CIA
whistleblower uh he has his own
newsletter which I think is just John
kiriaku.substack.com that you can go
subscribe you call it loud and clear
loud and clear with John kiriaku yes yep
and uh that goes back to what you did
with Paul Wright and uh I used to be a
regular on uh your show and also right
and also uh your contributor to
Consortium news and so welcome back
thank you we've been doing these
conversations on uh developments with
Donald Trump unfortunately I didn't get
one in with the with Joe Biden but
frankly I found it to be kind of lame
like the news was trying to squeeze
something out of nothing although there
is a little detail that I will ask you
about that I find somewhat fascinating
but now we're talking about well well
we're talking about this so I'll just go
ahead and let this uh local news
broadcast do the work of setting it up
classified documents are making
headlines from former president Donald
Trump and former vice president Mike
Pence to sitting President Joe Biden but
it's not a unique problem for
high-ranking government leaders in fact
it goes all the way back to Jimmy
Carter's president see in a new report
an anonymous source tells the Associated
Press that former officials turn over
classified information they found
several times a year in fact One Source
says Carter once found classified
materials at his home in Plains and
turned them over to the National
Archives President Carter himself
actually created the Presidential
records Act of 1978 just three years
before he left office that act namely
changed legal ownership of the official
records of the president from private to
public and it set up a new structure for
how presidents must manage records from
their administrations it didn't go into
effect for Carter's own presidency but
former President Carter still invited
Federal archivists to help him organize
his records before they went before they
were sent to his presidential library
right here in Atlanta right and then now
we're hearing that the National Archives
has sent a letter to just about every
representative of former presidential
administrations has said no know
if you got any records just let us know
we'd really like to have them back yes
yes we've we've really entered the
Absurd uh you know the the big issue
here and I know that you agree with me
on this the big issue here is the
overuse the misuse of the
unconstitutionally vague Espionage Act
um
in my own case I I was charged with
Espionage back in 2012. in my own case
my judge said
um that Espionage that she she would not
respect precedent
a precedent that was set in the Tom
Drake case and she said that that in my
case she was defining Espionage as
providing National Defense information
to any person not entitled to receive it
and my attorneys jumped up and one of
them said your honor wait are you saying
that a person can accidentally commit
Espionage and she said that's exactly
what I'm saying and she looked at me and
she said Mr kiriaku you either did it or
you didn't do it and I think you did it
well guess what
that
unconstitutionally broad uh uh
definition of an unconstitutionally
broad law
means that Donald Trump Joe Biden
um uh Mike Pence and who knows who else
are technically guilty of having
committed Espionage the way that the
Espionage Act has been using is being
used today makes them guilty now are
they guilty of Espionage of course not
should they be prosecuted for Espionage
of course not but this gives us an
opportunity
to scrap this terrible law and to
rewrite it
so that people who are guilty of
Espionage people working for our enemies
people working on behalf of foreign
governments or foreign powers can be
prosecuted rightfully prosecuted and
whistleblowers and people who
accidentally take home a classified
document are not subject to this
Draconian law
right what we are seeing is that the
justice department has actually created
this dilemma and where in which they
find themselves where they actually
should be following their own practice
and indict all of these people everybody
being found with documents yes and what
we're learning is in fact they were
wrong to charge all of you you reality
winner anybody else Stephen Kim whomever
who had documents that they should have
charged them with a misdemeanor of
mishandling classified information
because then in this situation
it would be fine to look the other way
it would be fine to treat it as just
like nothing that anybody should really
worry about but now just just to do a
quick accounting of it we we hear that
Mike Pence
first he says he doesn't have any
documents very
confidently and then documents are found
in his possession and we we learned that
they actually were briefings from
foreign trips that he took as vice
president which by the way that's that's
not something to just shrug off because
to me that's about 50 of the state
Embassy cables that were published by
Wikileaks which they still refused to
declassify still treat as like highly
sensitive material right most of those
half of those are background briefings
that's exactly what Mike Pence had I
would go supposed to say I would go so
far as to say that what Mike Pence has
is is more serious than what Julian
Assange released because those briefing
papers those those briefing
um uh well they call them briefing books
that Mike Pence has include
finished CIA intelligence for example
psychological profiles of the foreign
leaders that he's going to meet with
that's very highly classified Julian
Assange never released anything as
highly classified as that so this is
this is worse than than what Julian
Assange is being accused of having done
and then one thing we're
we're uh in relation to Biden this is
the part of what he did that I think
deserves the most attention is that they
found documents they believe he took
when he was a Senator yeah when he was a
Senator and you've got
Senators like Mark Warner and Marco
Rubio and others who have to go through
all of these procedures to see documents
scratching their heads trying to figure
out what what is this what why did he
think he was exempt from the rules Kevin
this one worries me you know I spent I
spent two years plus as the senior
investigator on the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee staff
and if you're on any committee other
than the intelligence committee and and
Joe Biden when he was a Senator he was
the chairman of this of the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee
if you're on the Foreign Relations
Committee and you want to see classified
documents you have to go down to the
vaulted area
uh the vaulted conference room that's
managed by the Senate security officer
right you can't just have classified
documents in your office because your
office is not a vaulted area it's not a
secure area so you cannot have
classified documents there if you wanted
to read a briefing or to read
international cable traffic you go down
to the office of the Senate security
officer which is underneath the capital
Rotunda
you make an appointment there you go
down there they take you into the
classified uh uh Vault the conference
room
and you can read those documents there
you can't walk out with classified
documents like you have to make an
effort to walk out with classified
documents and if Joe Biden had
classified documents from his time as a
senator he tried to take out those
documents this is one of those issues
that I think he's going to have to
answer for to the American people and to
explain
you know classified docs from your
Senate days those don't accidentally get
into your stuff
he's going to have to explain it and
what we're hearing also is that emphasis
on inadvertently I'd like to play this
clip I don't
have a lot of respect for the person
asking this question but frankly it
doesn't matter
but I want to play to you what John
Kirby who uh was was asked about
um he's some official in the uh Biden
Administration and I just want to play
what he was saying in response to a
question about you know particularly how
does this happen how do documents leave
a skiff and what should happen to
somebody if they take documents that's
it to walk out of a skiff with
classified material
everybody who goes in to a skiff
uh knows what the requirements are to go
in
um and knows uh what the requirements
are to go out
um you know there's you can't bring
personal devices in and uh you certainly
can't leave uh with material unless that
material is appropriately secured
and usually what happens to someone in
the chain of command if they do leave
with a piece of classified material that
they're not supposed to have or that is
not secured I think uh if
if you do it inadvertently or you do it
and you really you realize you know you
don't have it secured in a locked bag or
you know you
you self-report
which is exactly what the president did
self-reported
um but you self-report and you uh you
make sure that uh that you get the
material back secured where it belongs
um and that you're transparent about it
okay yes and no I mean is it that easy I
mean I'm thinking of people who are low
level who I really care about who might
find they have a document how do they
convince their superiors that they
weren't doing it deliberately well I I
think I can shed some light on this if
you if you walk out of a skiff and you
want to take classified documents with
you there are two ways to do it you have
to put it in an envelope seal it Mark
the classification on the front and back
of the envelope put it in another
envelope seal it again
and then put the address of your home
Agency on it and then you carry it with
you and God help you you better not drop
it or lose it or you know leave it
somewhere right
or
your agency puts it in a uh it it's a
leather bag with a double lock on it
and you you put it in an envelope and
then put the envelope in the leather bag
and lock it and take it back to your
agency
I've honestly never heard of somebody
just walking out of a skiff with
classified documents and just kind of
forgetting about it for you know 12
years
and just finding it in his garage in a
box that that's just not that doesn't
happen in real life now with that said I
want to give you an indication of how
things have changed over the years when
I was when I was at the CIA uh I sat
next to a woman
who had an affair with a former senior
Cia officer who had become a commentator
on CNN
and in the course of you know their
relationship pillow talk she she said
something to him that was classified
he went on to CNN and he repeated what
she had told him
the CIA immediately began an
investigation and they very quickly
zeroed right in on her they called her
into security and they asked did you
give this information to this guy who
then broadcasted on CNN she said yes I
did right now today
she would be charged with Espionage and
she would do
if we look at the reality winner case
which is one of the most recent she
would do about five years in prison
but what they did with her
is they suspended her for four weeks
without pay and they put a very strongly
worded memo in her file
saying that she did this and that was it
now that's how they should have dealt
with it she didn't commit Espionage she
did something stupid was there any harm
to the National Security no there wasn't
but by God she'll never do it again
because of that punishment
so how did we get in 20 short years
how did we get from from that this this
sane approach to to the disclosure of
classified information to just wantingly
charging everybody with Espionage it
doesn't make sense to me I'm I'm
cautiously hopeful
that this situation between Biden and
Trump and Pence and whoever else happens
to come forward and I think there
probably will be others
makes makes the situation so ridiculous
that Congress is forced to take a closer
look at reforming the Espionage Act
otherwise it's just going to get worse
and we're going to have to charge
everybody with Espionage I mean in your
pool who who who has documents next I
mean I should we take Barack Obama we
haven't heard without a doubt from
Barack Obama yeah but I imagine he might
have a document perhaps on the the
targeted killing program he protect
perfected just yeah just to keep for his
own legacy and and it turns out it
actually uh shouldn't be released
because they were fighting the ACLU or
the center for constitutional rights in
court and or so I'm thinking I'm
imagining of something that absurd you
know I I saw I think it was in the New
York Times yesterday that Bill Clinton
and and both bushes have been cleared
that there's no classified documents uh
in their personal possession there are
no classified documents that are
inappropriately housed or stored at
their presidential libraries nobody said
anything about Barack Obama and so I I
think I think you're on to something
here I think probably the next
announcement that we hear is oh my gosh
how did this happen but Barack Obama has
classified documents whether they're in
that storage facility and outside of
Chicago where they're awaiting the
building of his Presidential Library or
at his 14 million dollar Oceanfront
mansion on Cape Cod
my guess is that's what we hear next
yeah and and just a quick aside from me
personally as a Chicago resident the
construction of his library is a scandal
it's it's in a it it's it was uh a slap
in the face for the whole community on
the south side that had to give up all
this property for this monstrous this
gaudy monstrosity that he's going to
construct on the lakefront uh anyways uh
and I it's not even going to have
documents it's not even going to be a
library so there's not even any academic
contribution that he's watching you the
whole point that should be the whole
point is for Scholars to be able to go
to these presidential libraries and read
these documents and use them you know in
scholarly Publications or their PHD
dissertations or whatever they shouldn't
be they shouldn't be Alters to uh
to you know self-promoting greatness
so before we uh wrap this up I have a
few quick clips I want to run by you
because I think it touches on some
aspects of this that I'm really glad
someone with a wide platform was able to
bring up so uh Jon Stewart has this
podcast called the problem that is done
by Apple TV plus you just did a
conversation that went for about 45
minutes I found a lot of it pretty
fascinating with someone from Columbia
University named Matthew Connelly who
has a book that was just released called
the declassification engine and he spent
like the last 10 years examining wide
overclassification is such a problem and
I think this is really what more of our
conversations should be focused upon so
I just want to get your reaction to a
few of these points that that came up
rather organically
um and also I'll just say that I was
kind of impressed I'm I mean I'm I'm I
was gratified to learn that somebody who
does this is spending so much time
talking about politics and these issues
actually seems very sympathetic and
empathetic to what has unfairly happened
to Chelsea Manning reality winner and
Julian Assange and and did get it right
so here I'm gonna play this first clip
yeah so for an example when I first
started out I mentioned how it was about
10 years ago I got together with some
colleagues in the statistics department
and computer science and we had this
idea hey you know there's all the
secrecy and there are millions now
millions of Declassified documents and
who knows how many still classified
billions uh probably and we thought you
know why don't we begin using like these
data science tools to get to the bottom
of this like let's start figuring out
like what is like an actual top secret
and and what is really something that's
already in the public domains people you
know things that people should already
know and what we found is that there are
lawyers out there you know former
government lawyers uh you know one of
them was the general counsel of the NSA
another one was they had a major crimes
at the southern district these lawyers
uh told us that we could get prosecuted
under the Espionage Act just for
analyzing Declassified documents you
know so it's not just like yes
now in God's name you can be prosecuted
for Espionage by analyzing Declassified
information that's the theory that
doesn't make any sense if you go to a
very fancy law school it's got to be a
fancy one it has to be fancy and you get
paid a thousand dollars an hour you can
come up with all kinds of theories
he's right it's called the Mosaic
concept yep it's something that the that
the Soviets came up with in the 1960s
where they believed that if you if you
look at enough
unclassified
or Declassified information you can put
pieces of this Mosaic together or puzzle
together to come up with a classified
program
and so it's something that the United
States has long struggled with but he's
absolutely right if if there was some uh
some prosecutor in the southern district
of New York or more
more likely in the eastern district of
Virginia who wanted to make a name for
himself
um sure I could see I could see a
professor uh being charged with
Espionage for looking at unclassified or
Declassified information absolutely
yeah so I was looking at something from
the information security overs it's the
iso
um that is in charge of doing these
reports annually and examining the
classification system uh they're
supposed to do some oversight and it's
really hard job that they have because
they just don't really have much power
over what the executive branch does and
the choices that these agencies make
but I noticed that even they were and
this is this is wild to me they were
suggesting that uh controlled
unclassified information or they say cui
which isn't secret it's not top secret
but controlled unclassified information
is not covered by The Insider threat
program yes and that they should expand
it so that they have uh are trying to
track and monitor any threats of people
like taking controlled
um classified information which is just
like just this metastasization of this
getting worse and worse yeah that's the
word for it in the intelligence
community that information is is called
sbu sensitive but unclassified
yeah yeah it's not a classification it's
a control
so
so things that have sbu on them are like
um a training manual
for how to clean a gun
right
or
um the department of commerce's trade
numbers that are going to come out in
three days
those are sensitive but unclassified
they have nothing to do with sources and
methods
they may potentially possibly cause a
little bit of embarrassment if they were
to leak but they are not classified and
to to include information like that
under the the Espionage Act
would be to add an entire layer of
federal employees
underneath the Espionage acts auspices
people who for example people at the
office of personnel management okay
nobody at the office of personnel
management has access to classified
information they don't need access to
classified information so everything
that they do because it's Personnel
based it's sensitive but unclassified
well let's say uh you know you're a
really hard worker you're a branch chief
at the office of personnel management
and you need to really finish these
Personnel uh updates so you take some of
the some of the files home with you and
you accidentally leave them on the
subway
what you're going to be charged with
Espionage come on
this is really entering the realm of the
of the Absurd
yeah but it's also like a window into
this National secrecy complex and and
how much of a like psychosis these
people have of this need to protect and
I just wanna I know you know this but I
want people who hear us having this
conversation or watch us have this
conversation recognize what like so you
can't really tell what this document is
but what I'm going to tell you by
pointing out these black bars is that
this is the redaction of how much money
they're spending to declassify
information you're not even allowed to
know how much money the CIA spends on
deep classification systems or what NSA
spends on B classification systems or
what the National geospatial
Intelligence Agency or the odni the
office of the director for you're not
allowed to know what they're spending
that is
outrageous and it's typical and very
common you know we only know we only
have a general idea of what the CIA
spends because the former deputy
National deputy director of National
Intelligence Mary Margaret Graham
accidentally let it slip while giving a
speech during the Obama Administration
otherwise we wouldn't have any idea what
the budget is the budget has always been
classified
yeah all right so I got one more clip I
split it into two just for the sake of
talking points but it's about a minute
and a half and then we'll wrap this up
uh so here
so in 2012 they said it was over 90
million times so that's three times
every second three times every second
somebody is saying yeah this is
classified right and just the other day
I was looking at a document from The
Carter Administration back in 1977 they
were trying to do something about this
you know impossible problem and the NSA
the National Security Agency the people
like who spy on everyone
um and surveillance they try to get
Exempted entirely you know from the
whole system for trying to review and
release information and one argument
they made was that request
was that a top secret request it was in
the Carter library for decades before we
we had found this document with a bunch
of other documents so the figure they
gave is they said how are we supposed to
declassify stuff we produced 10 000
secret reports a day
so this is back in 1977. can you imagine
what the volume is now it's estimated
the state department even I think it was
like eight or ten years ago the state
Department's producing two billion email
a day right so how are you going to
control and protect all those secrets
yeah that's right
that's right I remember I was overseas I
was on an overseas uh temporary Duty
with the CIA on the day that classified
email was implemented and I remember the
station chief that I was working for
saying we thought things were out of
hand already there's no way to control
classified email and you know I've
mentioned to you in the past Kevin
that at the CIA and at NSA and DOD and
NSC and so many of these other
organizations literally everything that
is produced gets a classification on it
even when it is legitimately
unclassified for example I would write
an email to my wife who was also a
senior Cia officer and I'd say do you
want to meet for lunch and I would
classify it secret because every CI
employee has classification Authority
secret hum 4-82 which is the the actual
Authority human intelligence
and she would respond sure let's meet in
front of the deli at 12 and she would
classify
her response Secret
hum 4-82 well it's not secret that I
want to meet my wife for lunch it's not
secret that we're going to meet at noon
in front of the deli but that's just how
you're taught how you're trained to do
it where everything is classified
because they say look if if you make it
unclassified some Malignant Force out
there the Russians the Chinese whomever
they might be able to put it together
and come up with some classified
information
as a result you have billions and
billions of classified documents being
created every single year
with no mechanism to police them or to
eventually declassify them
and uh and just very quickly and then
I'll play the the rest of the clip that
I have uh are in your mind our officials
stamping these documents secret because
they want their boss or Superior to give
them attention that's something that
this uh that that Connolly says in this
conversation with Jon Stewart that he
believes that uh there's there's so many
documents that get classified just
because that makes them important to the
person at the agency oh without a doubt
not so much at the CIA because
everything's classified anyway but at
some of these lesser agencies absolutely
absolutely it makes you feel like you
know you're one of the In Crowd you're
one of the you know the special people
that has access maybe the guy you sit
next to he doesn't have access so you're
more you're more important than he is
you see that every day
yeah so I found that in fiscal year 2015
this was flagged by the project on
government oversight that uh they do
these this thing called classification
challenges
um which is a natural uh procedure that
is uh apparently built into some of
these agencies if you're confident that
certain information has been classified
inappropriately you you you and you have
a challenge and then what they found was
nearly half of the classification
challenges
ended up overturning the initial
classification decision of that year now
it's much lower maybe they're doing a
better job I don't know what but that to
me is like quite a statement of how far
afield this whole system has gone and so
um let's close I've got uh Jon Stewart
making what I think is the essential
point and then I'll get your response to
it and then we'll get out of here and
the crazy part is it doesn't feel as
though
journalists have any sense of how to put
any of this into context they own right
now they are chasing something that they
believe is spy versus spy Trump V Biden
when they're not looking at the broader
absurdity of the entire National
Security State
so true
so completely true there are very very
few journalists certainly none in the
mainstream that that I've encountered
who really have a full appreciation for
what this uh this issue is
yeah I'm glad that you're that you're
doing this because you understand the
problem the problem isn't who found how
many documents in whose garage
the the problem is why are these
documents classified in the first place
yep and the problem isn't who is this
going to be worse for in the 2024
election exactly and and uh oh if uh if
if Biden apologizes does that mean that
we can still prosecute Trump or does it
mean that Trump doesn't get to use Biden
to his benefit to get people to vote for
him and it's it's like it's the most
mind-numbing stupidity for them to go
back and forth and I don't see how you
can even
try and pull this and make it seem like
it's a relevant issue I just don't think
I have to say this for people who got
through this video and and go well why
do I care about classified documents
it's not that's not anything in my daily
life that I have to deal with that's not
anything that I have to worry about when
I'm working my job trying to put food on
the table uh trying to figure out how to
pay my bills and take care of my debts I
understand that completely and I think
that's what's insane but
um there was
there was this one comment I read from
this uh low ranking
officer I'm gonna I'm gonna I'm gonna
I'm gonna read this to you and and
conclude with this because I found it
this is just it's just a YouTube comment
uh and normally I would think it's
completely insignificant but I find this
to be just like why I believe what we're
observing in this country has struck
such a nerve and um here this comes from
his name's Tony and he says I spent many
years in the military and as a civilian
handling classified documents and
materials as a classified document
custodian it was my responsibility to
ensure that any document that was under
my control was signed for and when
returned signed back into the filing
system
these signatures were required for
anyone that removed a document from my
control if that document was not
returned within a specified time frame
it was reported and an immediate
investigation was conducted how the hell
does this crap happen with the people
that we have entrusted with our safety
and our protection are these people so
far above the law that they just don't
give a damn
I really empathize with that I do too
I do too
yeah we should put we should put him on
the Blue Ribbon panel to uh to
declassify these billions of documents
yeah I mean all of these people I mean
at this point I think
you know nearly half of it has to be
Declassified but you know the problem is
two that uh the agencies can't keep up
with the amount of information that
needs to be Declassified now they just
bureaucratically don't have the staff
and resources for it it's not going to
be funded by Congress and then two they
don't want to declassify these materials
and so anyways if you have uh like 25
years is up and let's say all the
material in Obama's administration
should be Declassified well then they're
going to go through it and try to find a
new reason why it should be delayed as
far as declassification some of that
might be administrative uh just to cut
them a break so they have less volume of
material but some of it's going to be
because they don't want us to have
certain materials and uh
and so it you know if that's the case
and you just have uh officials that are
going to just abscond and take off with
material
for their Memoirs or whatever they're
going to do with it or just to keep it
in storage I guess just like
I don't know
I'm sort of like imagining this like
absurdity of uh of like a storage unit
on like Pawn Stars and then you pull up
the garage and then you find out that
not only are there antiques there but
Joe Biden also has some like documents
in his in his uh storage unit that yeah
exactly on this reality show
anyways
thank you John thank you for your time I
appreciate it uh maybe you want to take
a moment to tell people where they can
find your work once again thank you
thank you I've moved everything over to
sub stack so it's John
kiriaku.substack.com it's called
um loud and clear with John kiriaku
thanks for checking it out all right
everyone